<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<courses>
<course id="CMSC104" name="Problem Solving and Computer Programming" credits="3">
	<description>This course is designed to provide an introduction to problem solving and computer programming that does not require prior programming experience. Elementary problem solving skills and algorithm development will be 
introduced. Students will be taught the basic use of a programming environment and basic programming constructs (including loops, control statements, functions, and arrays). This course also teaches students the fundamentals of using the UNIX operating system, and introduces general computer science concepts. Note: This course does not fulfill any of the computer science major requirements. Students who have taken and received transfer credit for, or who are taking concurrently any computer programming course in a high-level programming language, will not receive credit for CMSC 104. The list of such computer programming courses includes, but is not limited to AP Computer Science, CMSC 201, CMSC 202, and sections of CMSC 291 that cover programming topics.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="CMSC201" name="Computer Science I for Majors" credits="4">
	<description>An introduction to computer science through problem solving and computer programming. Programming techniques covered by this course include modularity, abstraction, top-down design, specifications documentation, debugging and testing. The core material for this course includes control structures, functions, lists, strings, abstract data types, file I/O, and recursion. It is assumed that students already know the basics of a modern high level language such as Java, Python, or C (expressions, basic data types, arrays/lists, and control structures).</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="CMSC202" name="Computer Science II for Majors" credits="4">
	<description>This course continues the student's development of programming and problem-solving skills by providing an introduction to object-oriented design and programming (OOP). The primary focus is on OOP principles and techniques, including encapsulation, composition, inheritance, and polymorphism. Other OOP topics such as exception handling, containers, and generic programming are also covered. This is the second course for students interested in pursuing further study in computer science.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC201</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC203" name="Discrete Structures" satisfies="M" credits="3">
	<description>This course introduces the fundamental tools, topics and concepts of discrete mathematics needed to study computer science. This course emphasizes counting methods, proof techniques and problem solving strategies. Topics include Boolean algebra; set theory; symbolic logic; predicate calculus; number theory; the methods of direct, indirect and inductive proofs; objective functions; equivalence relations; graphs; set partitions; combinatorics; modular arithmetic; summations; and recurrences.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH151</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC304" name="Social and Ethical Issues in Information Technology" satisfies="AH" credits="3">
	<description>A survey course that reviews social issues and the ethical impact of information technology throughout the world. The course examines the policy issues that relate to the use of information technology, such as persona, privacy, rights of access, security, transborder information flow and confidentiality.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC202</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC313" name="Computer Organization and Assembly Language Programming" credits="3">
	<description>This course introduces the student to the low-level abstraction of a computer system from a programmer's point of view, with an emphasis on low-level programming. Topics include data representation, assembly language programming, C programming, the process of compiling and linking, low-level memory management, exceptional control flow, and basic processor architecture.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC202</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC203</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC331" name="Principles of Programming Languages" credits="3">
	<description>This course examines the theory, design and implementation of programming languages and provides students with an introduction to programming languages that are likely to be new to them. Topics include specifications of syntax and semantics, declarations, binding, allocation, data structures, data types, control structures, control and data flow, concurrency, and the implementation and execution of programs. The major language paradigms will be described and explored, including imperative, object-oriented, functional, logic programming, concurrent and others. Programming projects will provide experience in several languages.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC202</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC203</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC341" name="Data Structures" credits="3">
	<description>An examination of a range of advanced data structures, with an emphasis on an object-oriented approach. Topics include asymptotic analysis; various binary search trees, including red-black and splay trees; skip lists as alternatives to binary search trees; data structures for multidimensional data such as K-D trees; heaps and priority queues, including binary heaps, binomial heaps, leftist heaps (and/or other mergeable heaps); B-trees for external storage; other commonly used data structures, such as hash tables and disjoint sets. Programming projects in this course will focus on implementation issues for data structures and on empirical analysis of their asymptotic performance.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC202</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC203</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC345" name="Software Design and Development" satisfies="WI" credits="3">
	<description>This course introduces the basic concepts of software engineering, including software life cycle, requirements analysis and software design methods. Professional ethics in computer science and the social impact of computing are discussed as an integral part of the software development process. Additional topics may include tools for software development, software testing, software metrics and software maintenance.</description>
	<prerequisites>
	<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC411" name="Computer Architecture" credits="3">
	<description>This course covers the design of complex computer systems making heavy use of the components and techniques discussed in CMSC 313, CMPE 212 and CMPE 310. All parts of the computer system - CPU, memory and input/output - are discussed in detail. Topics include information representation, floating-point arithmetic, instructions set design issues (RISC vs. CISC), microprogrammed control, hardwired control, pipelining, memory cashes, bus control and timing,input/output mechanism and issues in the construction of parallel processors.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC313</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC421" name="Principles of Operating Systems" credits="3">
	<description>An introduction to the fundamentals of operating systems. Topics include interprocess communication, process scheduling, deadlock, memory management, virtual memory, file systems and distributed systems. Formal principles are illustrated with examples and case studies of one or more contemporary operating systems. </description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC313</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC426" name="Principles of Computer Security" credits="3">
	<description>This course will provide an introduction to computer security, with specific focus on the computing aspects. Topics covered will include: Basics of computer security including an overview of threat, attack, and adversary models; social engineering; essentials of cryptography; traditional computing security models; malicious software; secure programming; Operating system security in practice; trusted operating system design; public policy issues including legal, privacy, and ethical issues; network and database security overview. </description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC421</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC427" name="Wearable Computing" credits="3">
	<description>This course covers fundamental concepts, methodologies, and algorithms related to wearable computing, including the following: Emotional Design, Convergent Design Processes, Wearability Considerations, Wearable Sensors Networks, Wearable Networks, Physiological Wearable Sensors, Innovation Processes, Marketing and business considerations, Human Aware Computing, Context Awareness, Wearable Communities, Future Mobility and Wearable Systems Applications.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="CMSC431" name="Compiler Design Principles" credits="3">
	<description>A detailed study of the design and implementation of a compiler for a high-level programming language. Topics include lexical analysis, parsing techniques (including LL and LR parsers), semantic routines,run-time storage allocation, code generation and optimization.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC313</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC331</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC432" name="Object-Oriented Programming Languages and Systems" credits="3">
	<description>This course covers the concepts of object-oriented programming (OOP) languages and systems, including an introduction to fundamental abstraction, modularity and encapsulation mechanisms in OOP from a software engineering and representational perspective. Basic OOP concepts covered in this course include polymorphism and operator overloading, message passing via generic functions, late- vs. early-binding times, and inheritance mechanisms and their relationship to the type systems of programming languages. Other topics include a survey of OOP languages and systems, OOP languages vs. imperative programming languages and contrasting pure OOP environments vs. mixed paradigm languages.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC331</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC433" name="Scripting Languages" credits="3">
	<description>This course is a study of a class of programming languages and tools known as scripting languages. Topics include: writing scripts to control and connect other programs, strengths and weaknesses of interpreted languages, extending scripting languages to include new functionality, embedding functions of a scripting language in other tools, and the syntax and usage of regular expressions. Programming projects in multiple languages will be required.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC331</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC435" name="Computer Graphics" credits="3">
	<description>An introduction to the fundamentals of interactive computer graphics. Topics include graphics hardware, line drawing, area filling, clipping, two-dimensional and three-dimensional geometrical transforms, three-dimensional perspective viewing, hidden surface removal, illumination, color and shading models.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC313</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MATH221</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC436" name="Data Visualization" credits="3">
	<description>This course addresses the theoretical and practical issues in creating visual representations of large amounts of data.  It covers the core topics in data visualization: data representation, visualization toolkits, scientific visualization, medical visualization, information visualization, and volume rendering techniques.  Additionally, the related topics of applied human perception and advanced display devices are introduced.  Open to computer science students with a background in computer graphics or students in data-intensive fields who are familiar with the use of the computer for data collection, storage or analysis.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC435</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC437" name="Graphical User Interface Programming" credits="3">
	<description>This is a practical, hands-on course in how to program interactive 2-D graphical user interfaces using the X11/Motif package and OpenGL. Graphical user interfaces are taken here to mean not just standard widget sets, but also various interactive, pointer-based techniques that comprise the modern desktop metaphor. This course also will introduce some of the concepts and software techniques used to implement such applications. In addition, it briefly will review some of the larger issues, history and future directions of programming graphical interfaces.While the primary emphasis of the course is on 2-D interfaces, there will be a short introduction to some of the 3-D capabilities of OpenGL,as well as a discussion of 3-D interaction and virtual reality.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH221</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC441" name="Design and Analysis of Algorithms" credits="3">
	<description>This course studies fundamental algorithms, strategies for designing algorithms, and mathematical tools for analyzing algorithms. Fundamental algorithms studied in this course include algorithms for sorting and searching, hashing, and graph algorithms. Mathematical tools include asymptotic notations and methods for solving recurrences. Algorithm design strategies include the greedy method, divide-and-conquer, dynamic programming, and randomization.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH152</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>STAT355</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC442" name="Information and Coding Theory" credits="3">
	<description>An introduction to information and coding theory. Topics include error-control coding problems, entropy, channels, Shannon's theorems, error-correcting codes, applications of coding theory, algebraic codingtheory, block codes, linear codes, cyclic codes, decoding algorithms, BCH codes, convolutional codes, linear sequential circuits and sequential decoding.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH221</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC203</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC443" name="Cryptology" credits="3">
	<description>An introduction to cryptology, the science of making and breaking codes and ciphers. Topics include: conventional and public-key cryptosystems, including DES, RSA, shift register systems and selected classical systems; examples of cryptanalytic techniques; digital signatures; pseudo-random number generation; cryptographic protocols and their applications; and an introduction to the theories of cryptographic strength based on information theory and complexity theory.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MATH221</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>STAT355</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC444" name="Information Assurance" credits="3">
	<description>Selected recent research topics in information assurance, such as social engineering, buffer overflow, malicious code, spyware, denial of service, information warfare, computer forensics, recovery and response, enterprise security, clandestine channels and emissions security, security analysis, security models and formal techniques, best practices, and national policy for information assurance. Taking a broad, practical view of security - including people, policies and procedures, and technology - this course will help students devise and implement security solutions that meaningfully raise the level of confidence in computer systems. This course will minimize discussion of intrusion detection, firewalls, operating systems security, and mathematical cryptology, which are emphasized in other CMSC security courses.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC421</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC481</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC445" name="Software Engineering" credits="3">
	<description>A continuation of the study of software engineering with emphasis on topics not fully covered in CMSC 345. Topics may include software maintenance; metrics; quality assurance; configuration management; deployment; project planning and management; and modern software development processes, techniques and tools. Students will be given multiple individual and cooperative hands-on assignments.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC345</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC446" name="Introduction to Design Patterns" credits="3">
	<description>This course is an introduction to software design patterns. Each pattern represents a best practice solution to a software problem in some context. The course will cover the rationale and benefits of object-oriented software design patterns. Several example problems will be studied to investigate the development of good design patterns.Specific patterns, such as observer, state, adapter, strategy, decorator and abstract factory will be discussed. Programming projects in the Java language will provide experience in the use of these patterns. In addition, distributed object frameworks, such as RMI and Jini, will be studied for their effective use of design patterns.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC331</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC451" name="Automata Theory and Formal Languages" credits="3">
	<description>This course introduces the basic concepts in the theory of formal languages. Topics include regular grammars and finite automata, context-free grammars and push-down automata, Turing machines and the halting problem, and an introductory treatment of computable and non-computable functions.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC202</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC203</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC452" name="Logic for Computer Science" credits="3">
	<description>This course covers the fundamental topics in sentential and first-order logic, including models, logical consequence, deduction and the completeness theorem. Other topics include: undecidability theorems, including Goedel's incompleteness theorem and Tarski's theorem; Herbrand's theorem; and applications including resolution, logic programming, automatic deduction, program specification and program verification.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC203</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC453" name="Applied Combinatorics and Graph Theory" credits="3">
	<description>An introduction to the application of combinatorial methods to computer science. Topics include enumeration methods, recurrence relations, generating functions, graph theory and graph algorithms, and connectivity, Euler tours, Hamiltonian cycles, flow graphs and transport networks, matching theory, planarity, Kuratowski's theorem and NP-complete combinatorial problems.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MATH221</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MATH152</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC455" name="Numerical Computations" credits="3">
	<description>Topics include numerical linear algebra, interpolation, solving non-linear systems and the numerical solution of differential equations. This course also provides some emphasis on numerical algorithms andcomputation in a parallel environment.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MATH152</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MATH221</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC456" name="Symbolic Computation" credits="3">
	<description>The theme of this course is abstract algebra from an algorithmic perspective. Algorithms for computing in groups, rings, fields, ideals, quotient rings and other algebraic objects are studied. For example, the Coxeter coset enumeration and the Groebner basis algorithms are studied. Algebraic varieties play a key role in this course. The course also covers many applications of symbolic computation, such as applications to algebraic coding theory, robotics and automatic theorem proving. There are various projects using a symbolic computation package such as Maple or Mathematica.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MATH152</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MATH221</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC457" name="Quantum Computation" credits="3">
	<description>The course begins with a brief overview of those topics in quantum mechanics and mathematics needed for the understanding of quantum computation. It will then focus on quantum algorithms, covering such topics as quantum superposition and quantum entanglement, quantum decoherence, quantum teleportation, quantum Turing machines, Shor's Algorithm, Grover's algorithm, Hallgren's algorithm, quantum information theory, quantum data compression, quantum cryptographic protocols, quantum error-correcting codes, implementation issues.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC203</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MATH221</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC461" name="Database Management Systems" credits="3">
	<description>This course covers database management and the different data models used to structure the logical view of databases. The course also covers database design and implementation techniques, including file organization, query processing, concurrency control, recovery, integrity and security.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC465" name="Introduction to Electronic Commerce" credits="3">
	<description>Electronic commerce is the use of electronic means to pursue business objectives. It relies on a wide range of modern technologies, such as the World Wide Web, telecommunications, database technologies, agent technologies, business intelligence, multimedia and user interfaces. This course puts special emphasis on the student's ability to do research in existing and emerging technology and to summarize and present findings clearly. An important part of this course is the development of technical writing skills. The second part of the course concentrates on the issues that are not solely technical, such as trust management, privacy and personalization, and the role of electronic market in revolutionizing traditional industries.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC461</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC481</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC466" name="Electronic Commerce Technology" credits="3">
	<description>This course is designed to prepare students to be e-commerce developers. It introduces students to the changing and competitive landscape of e-commerce technology, products and solutions. It begins with an introduction to WWW technology and an overview of Web applications and services. It further discusses networking technologies with the view toward mobile and wireless commerce and object orientation and Web programming. An overview of Java language and relational databases is given. Database-Web connectivity is discussed.The course proceeds with the study of inter-process communications in a distributed environment concentrating on Java RMI and COBRA technologies. Development of interactive Web pages with JavaScript and dynamic HTML, one of the basic skills in the area of e-commerce development, is covered.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC461</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC481</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC471" name="Introduction to Artificial Intelligence" credits="3">
	<description>This course provides a broad introduction to artificial intelligence, its sub-fields and their applications. Topics include problem-solving approaches, problem spaces and search, knowledge representation and reasoning, logic and deduction, planning, expert systems, handling uncertainty, learning and natural language understanding.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC473" name="Introduction to National Language Processing" credits="3">
	<description>Natural language processing (NLP), the first non-numerical application of computing, was first studied more than 50 years ago. The ultimate goal of NLP is to enable computers to communicate with people the same way that people communicate among themselves. To do so, the computers must be able to understand and generate text. The course will introduce the students to the problems, methods, and applications of NLP.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC331</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC475" name="Introduction to Neural Networks" credits="3">
	<description>This course is an in-depth introduction to neural networks. Topics include: characteristics of neural network computing; major neural network models and their related algorithms; supervised, unsupervised and reinforcement learning; and neural network application in function approximation, pattern analysis, optimization and associative memories.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC476" name="Information Retrieval" credits="3">
	<description>This course is an introduction to the theory and implementation of software systems designed to search through large collections of text. The first course objective is to cover the fundamentals of Information Retrieval (IR): retrieval models, search algorithms and IR evaluation. The second is to give a taste of the implementation issues through the construction and use of a text search engine.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC477" name="Agent Architectures and Multi-Agent Systems" credits="3">
	<description>This course covers fundamental techniques for developing intelligent agents and multi-agent systems, including cognitive, logic-based, reactive and belief-desire-intention architectures; inter-agent communication languages and protocols; distributed problem-solving, planning and constraint satisfaction methods; distributed models of rational behavior; and learning and adaptation in multi-agent systems.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC471</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC478" name="Introduction to Machine Learning" credits="3">
	<description>This course covers fundamental concepts, methodologies, and algorithms related to machine learning,which is the study of computer programs that improve some task with experience. Topics covered include decision trees, perceptrons, logistic regression, linear discriminant analysis, linear and non-linear regression, basic functions, support vector machines, neural networks, genetic algorithms, reinforcement learning, naive Bayes and Bayesian networks, bias/variance theory, ensemble methods, clustering, evaluation methodologies, and experiment design.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC471</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC479" name="Introduction to Robotics" credits="3">
	<description>This course covers fundamental concepts, methodologies, and algorithms related to autonomous mobile robotics, touching on mechanical, motor, sensory, perceptual, and cognitive aspects of the problem of building robots that move about and decide what to do on their own. Specific topics covered include legged and wheeled location, kinematic models and constraints, mobile robot maneuverability, motion control, sensors and sensing, perception, localization, belief representations, map representations, probabilistic map-based localization, autonomous map building, planning, reacting, and navigation architectures.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC471</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC481" name="Computer Networks" credits="3">
	<description>This course introduces the fundamentals of data communication and computer networking, including circuit and packet switching; network architectures and protocols; local/metropolitan/wide-area networks, OSI and TCP/IP standards; network programming and applications; and network management.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC483" name="Parallel and Distributed Processing" credits="3">
	<description>This course provides a project and applications-oriented approach to parallel and distributed programming. Students will learn a specific parallel language and programming environment and will complete a large programming project. Topics include a selected parallel programming language, a survey of parallel and distributed architectures and associated programming styles, an introduction to parallel and distributed algorithms, and a study of trade-offs between computation and communication in parallel processing.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC421</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC484" name="Java Server Technologies" credits="3">
	<description>This course is an in-depth look at several of the technologies currently in use to develop applications for the Web. Topics include the use of Java Servlets and Java Server Pages (JSP) and their benefits over traditional CGI programs, the development of web services using SOAP and XML, the use of Enterprise Java Beans to encapsulate server-side business logic and the use of application servers. Several programming projects will be done using these technologies and an appropriate Webserver, such as Apache Tomcat. In addition, several related technologies, such as PHP and Javascript, will be covered.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC202</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC486" name="Mobile Telephony Communications" credits="3">
	<description>This course is an in-depth look at several of the technologies currently in use to develop applications for the Web. Topics include the use of Java Servlets and Java Server Pages (JSP) and their benefits over traditional CGI programs, the development of web services using SOAP and XML, the use of Enterprise Java Beans to encapsulate server-side business logic and the use of application servers. Several programming projects will be done using these technologies and an appropriate Webserver, such as Apache Tomcat. In addition, several related technologies, such as PHP and Javascript, will be covered.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC202</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC487" name="Introduction To Network Security" credits="3">
	<description>The objective of this course is to teach the fundamental concepts, architectures, and protocols related to network security. Topics covered include: Overview of network security; Basics of cryptography; Threat models; Authentication and Authorization Mechanisms and Standards; Public Key Infrastructure; Electronic Mail Security; Network Layer Security; Transport layer and web security; Packet filtering; Firewalls; Intrusion Detection, and Virtual Private Networks; Recent topics in Network Security.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC341</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC421</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CSMC481</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CMSC491" name="Special Topics in Computer Science" credits="3">
	<description>Special topics in Computer Science. Prerequisite: Varies by topic. Check the current Schedule of Classes.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="CMSC493" name="Capstone Games Group Project" credits="3">
	<description>The computer games capstone course is designed to allow students completing the computer science games track to engage in a complete group project development experience. This will help them to integrate the various technical concepts they have learned in earlier courses. The course aims to impart a foundation in team leadership and project management ability that will allow graduates to function effectively within multi-disciplinary teams.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC435</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CMSC471</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="MATH150" name="Precalculus Mathematics" satisfies="M" credits="4">
	<description>This course provides the mathematical preparation necessary for success in calculus. It also provides preparation for basic physics, computer science and engineering science courses. Topics covered include review of functions and graphing techniques; logarithmic and exponential functions; review of basic right-angle trigonometry followed by an extensive treatment of trigonometric functions, identities and applications to the analytic geometry of the conic sections, applications to two-dimensional vectors and to the geometry of complex numbers.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="MATH151" name="Calculus and Analytic Geometry I" satisfies="M" credits="4">
	<description>Topics of this course include limits, continuity, the rate of change, derivatives, differentiations formulas for algebraic and trigonometric functions, maxima and minima, integration and computation of areas. Areas and volumes of solids of revolution, applications.   Note: Non-science oriented students should consider Math 155.  Credit will not be given for both Math 151 and Math 155.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
	<!-- 
		<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH150(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
	-->
</course>
<course id="MATH152" name="Calculus and Analytic Geometry II" satisfies="M" credits="4">
	<description>Topics of this course include logarithmic and exponential functions, inverse functions, methods of integration, improper integrals, hyperbolic functions, sequences and infinite series, power series, Taylor series, applications, conic sections and polar coordinates.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH151(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="MATH155" name="Applied Calculus" satisfies="M" credits="4">
	<description>Basic ideas of differential and integral calculus, with emphasis on elementary techniques of differentiation and integration with applications, are treated in this course. Technology will be utilized to enhance understanding of the concepts and their applications. Not recommended for students majoring in mathematics, computer science, engineering, or physical sciences.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="MATH215" name="Finite Mathematics for Information Science" credits="3">
	<description>This course focuses on the area of mathematics of particular use in the information sciences. The basic linear algebra of matrices used for solutions of large scale systems of linear equations is treated. Applications of matrices such as Leontieff models of multi-sector economics and the basics of the simples method for solving linear economic optimization problems are discussed. Fundamental concepts of probability including basic combinatorial methods for probabilistic computations are studied. An introduction is given to decision theory. This treatment is in the context of Bayesian or statistical decision theory, though game theoretic versions may be discussed. Possible optional topics may include elementary Markov chains or the matrix algebra of spreadsheet operations. </description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH151(C)|MATH155(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="MATH221" name="Introduction to Linear Algebra" satisfies="M" credits="3">
	<description>Topics of this course include: linear equations, Gauss-Jordan reduction, matrices and determinants and their properties, vector spaces and subspaces, basis and dimension, linear transformations, kernel and range, eigenvalues and eigenvectors, and matrix diagonalization</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH151</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="MATH225" name="Introduction to Differential Equations" satisfies="M" credits="3">
	<description>Topics of this course include: solutions of first- and second order linear differential equations, non-linear exact and separable equations, integrating factors, homogeneous equations, higher-order linear equations, initial and boundary value problems, solutions as functions of the equation parameters, Laplace transforms, power series solutions for Bessel and Legendre equations, difference equations and numerical methods.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH152(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="MATH251" name="Multivariable Calculus" satisfies="M" credits="4">
	<description>Topics of this course include: vectors, lines, planes and surfaces in three dimensions. Vector functions and their derivatives. Partial derivatives, gradients, directional derivatives, maxima, minima and Lagrange multipliers. Multiple integrals, area, volume, surface area, integration in different coordinate systems. Line integral, Green's theorem, Stokes' theorem and divergence theorem.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH152</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="MATH301" name="Introduction to Mathematical Analysis I" credits="4">
	<description>This course is a systematic study of basic analysis with an emphasis on formal proofs, examples and counter examples. Topics include properties of the real line, sequences, series, limits, continuity and differentiation of functions, and Riemann Integration.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH152(C)</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MATH221</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="MATH381" name="Linear Methods in Operations Research" credits="3">
	<description>Introduction to convex sets. Theory of linear programming. Applications to transportation and assignment problems. Introduction to graphs with applications to network problems, including shortest route and maximum flow problems. Introduction to game theory. </description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH221(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="MATH430" name="Matrix Analysis" credits="3">
	<description>Topics in this course will include a review of basic matrix operations, determinants,rank, matrix inverse and solving linear equations. The course then will study partitioned matrices, eigenvalues and eigenvectors, spectral decomposition, singular-value decomposition, orthogonal projections, idempotent matrices,quadratic forms, extrema of quadratic forms, non-negative definite and positive definite matrices, and matrix derivatives.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH251(C)</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MATH301(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="MATH441" name="Introduction to Numerical Analysis" credits="3">
	<description>Topics of this course include: numerical linear algebra, interpolation, numerical differentiation and integration, solution of nonlinear equations, acceleration of convergence and numerical treatment of differential equations.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC201</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MATH225(C)|MATH251(C)|MATH301(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="MATH452" name="Introduction to Stochastic Processes" credits="3">
	<description>This is a non-measure theoretic course. Topics include general Markov chains (branching process, queuing processes, birth and death processes, and Poisson processes), second-order processes (Gaussian processes and Wiener processes) and an introduction to stochastic differential equations.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>STAT355(C)|STAT451(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="MATH475" name="Combinatorics and Graph Theory" credits="3">
	<description>General enumeration methods, difference equations, generating functions. Elements of graph theory, including transport networks, matching theory and graph algorithms. Introduction to finite geometries and block designs.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH301(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="MATH481" name="Mathematical Modeling" satisfies="WI" credits="3">
	<description>Derivation and analysis of mathematical models of phenomena from physics, engineering and other exact sciences. Topics include stability of equilibria of dynamical systems with emphasis on the qualitative aspects of solutions, phase plane analysis and linearization of non-linear systems. Additional topics from catastrophe theory, bifurcation, optimization and chaos will be covered as time permits. Examples will be drawn from population dynamics, flywheel governor, a model for heartbeat, bang-bang controls, self-sustained oscillations and morphogenesis.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH221(C)|MATH225(C)|MATH251(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="MATH483" name="Linear and Combinatorial Optimization" credits="3">
	<description>Integer programming. The traveling salesman problem. Advanced linear programming techniques. Complexity. Projective methods in linear programming.The Karmarkar method.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH381(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="STAT351" name="Applied Statistics for Business and Economics" satisfies="M" credits="4">
	<description>Organization and presentation of data, summary of descriptive measures, probability, binomial, normal distributions and Pareto distribution, estimation of population parameters, sampling distributions, hypothesis testing, chi-square analysis, analysis of variance, linear regression and correlation, index numbers, time seried analysis and forecasting. Students will be introduced to statistical computing. All the statistical procedures will be illustrated using data from management, business and economics.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH150(C)|MATH151(C)|MATH152(C)|MATH155(C)|MATH225(C)|MATH251(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="STAT355" name="Introduction to Probability and Statistics for Scientists and Engineers" satisfies="M" credits="4">
	<description>An introduction to applied statistics designed for science majors and others with demonstrated quantitative ability. Topics include nature of statistical methods, random variables and their distribution functions, general principles of estimation and hypothesis testing. A laboratory introduces students to computer techniques in statistical analysis. </description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH152(C)|MATH225(C)|MATH251(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="STAT451" name="Introduction to Probability Theory" credits="3">
	<description>Topics include probability spaces and probability calculus, random variables and their distribution functions, the calculus of expectations, characteristic functions and large sample theory.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH251(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL100" name="Concepts of Biology" satisfies="S" credits="4">
	<description>A broad overview of contemporary biological science. Major areas include the biochemistry of energy transformation, cell structure and function, Mendelian, molecular and population genetics, development and differentiation, plant and animal physiology, evolution, and ecology.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="BIOL100L" name="Concepts of Experimental Biology" satisfies="LAB" credits="2">
	<description>The laboratory exercises are designed to provide the student experience with essential laboratory equipment and techniques.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>BIOL100(C)|BIOL141*|BIOL141|BIOL142*|BIOL142</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL141" name="Foundations of Biology: Cells, Energy and Organisms" satisfies="S" credits="4">
	<description>This course for majors provides a broad overview of contemporary biological concepts. Major topics include structure and synthesis of nucleic acids and proteins, molecular genetics, prokaryotic and eukaryotic cell structure and function, biochemistry of energy transformation, and animal and plant development and physiology. This course is designed to prepare students for upper level biology core and elective courses.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH150</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL142" name="Foundations of Biology: Ecology and Evolution" credits="4">
	<description>This course provides a broad overview of contemporary biological concepts. Major topics include fundamental concepts in ecology and evolution and emphasizes the fundamental interrelationship between these two fields of study. Concepts in evolution include a general description of the diversity of life, a review of Mendelian genetics, the causes and consequences of speciation, natural selection and genetic drift. Concepts in ecology will focus on ecological and evolutionary factors that govern population growth and regulation, species distributions, community and ecosystem ecology.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH1150</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL251" name="Human Anatomy and Physiology I" satisfies="S" credits="3">
	<description>The first semester of a two-semester lecture course covering the structure and function of the organs of the human body. An integrated approach permits concurrent presentation of the anatomy and physiology of each organ system.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>BIOL100</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CHEM102(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL251L" name="Human Anatomy and Physiology I Laboratory" satisfies="LAB" credits="2">
	<description>Laboratory course to accompany BIOL 251. The laboratory includes dissections, work with skeletons, models of body parts and experimental studies of physiological processes. Required for most allied health programs.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>BIOL100L</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CHEM102L(C)</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>BIOL251*|BIOL251(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL252" name="Human Anatomy and Physiology II" satisfies="S" credits="3">
	<description>Continuation of BIOL 251.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>BIOL251(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL252L" name="Human Anatomy and Physiology II Laboratory" satisfies="LAB" credits="2">
	<description>Continuation of BIOL 251L</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>BIOL251L(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL275" name="Microbiology" satisfies="S" credits="3">
	<description>Introductory course describing the fundamental properties of micro-organisms and viruses and their relationships to other life forms. Topics include the structure and function of bacteria, mode of action of antibiotics, genetics of bacteria and the role of bacteria in disease. The structure, replication and pathology of viruses are discussed, including the response of hosts to viral infection and the fundamental concepts of the immune response.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>BIOL100(C)|BIOL101(C)|BIOL141(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL275L" name="Microbology Laboratory" satisfies="LAB" credits="2">
	<description>This laboratory course consists of a series of exercises designed to familiarize the student with microbiological techniques. Experiments are performed in basic bacteriology, applied bacteriology, virology and immunology. Students will be expected to work independently, spending brief periods of time other than the scheduled lab period collecting data.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>BIOL275*|BIOL275(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL301" name="Ecology and Evolution" satisfies="S" credits="3">
	<description>An introduction to the processes of evolution, the outcomes of evolution, and the field of ecology. Processes of evolution include understanding natural selection, genetic drift, molecular evolution and general evolution theory. Outcomes of evolution includes speciation hybridization, building phylogenetic trees, and using trees to understand the diversity of life, especially vertebrate evolution. Ecology topics include population growth and regulation, competition, predator/prey interactions, symbiosis, community structure and food webs, and energy flow and nutrient cylcing within ecosystems. </description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>BIOL100(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL302" name="Molecular and General Genetics" satisfies="S" credits="3">
	<description>Modern principles of heredity have been established through studies at the molecular, cellular and organismic levels. The course includes fundamental information on the structure of a gene, its expression and organization as deduced from analysis of viral and prokaryotic systems, the transmission of genetic material in eukaryotic systems, the interaction of genes in populations and the application of fundamental genetic principles to problems of human heredity.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>BIOL100|BIOL141</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CHEM101(C)</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CHEM102*|CHEM102(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL302L" name="Molecular and General Genetics Laboratory" satisfies="LAB" credits="2">
	<description>A laboratory course designed to illustrate fundamental genetic principles by experimentation. Such principles include the nature of genetic material, transfer of genetic information in prokaryotic and eukaryotic systems, organization and regulation of gene expression, Mendel's rules of heredity, linkage and crossing over, and genetic variation. Students will be expected to work independently, spending periods of time outside the scheduled lab period collecting data.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>BIOL100L(C)</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>BIOL302(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL303" name="Cell Biology" credits="3">
	<description>A modern treatment of cell structure and function, with emphasis on the molecular architecture, biochemistry and regulatory mechanisms common to all cells. Topics include membrane structure, function and transport; molecular mechanisms of energy metabolism and its associated organelles; the structural and molecular basis for the expression of genetic information; the organelles involved in the regulation of cell shape and motility; and selected cell functions, growth, reproduction and their control. This course is designed for students interested in the biological sciences, biochemistry and the allied health professions.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>BIOL302(C)</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CHEM102(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL303L" name="Cell Biology Laboratory" satisfies="LAB" credits="2">
	<description>A course of laboratory experiments introducing students to the principles of experimental design and the analysis and interpretation of data in modern cell biology. Emphasis is placed on investigative approaches, critical thinking, and mathematical and writing skills important to practicing scientists. Experiments using the techniques of spectrophotometry, oxygen polarography, chromatography and tissue culture will be performed. This course is designed for students majoring in the biological sciences.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>BIOL100L(C)</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>BIOL303(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL304" name="Plant Biology" credits="3">
	<description>A modern treatment of the basic physiology and development of plants. Topics include special features of plant cell structure, patterns of growth and development, chloroplast development, photosynthesis, seed development, hormonal regulation, light regulation, phytochrome and photo-morphogenesis.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>BIOL303(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL304L" name="Plant Biology Laboratory" satisfies="LAB" credits="2">
	<description>A course of laboratory experiments designed to enhance student abilities in experimental design, hypothesis testing, and analysis and interpretation of data using plant systems. Students are required to present and interpret experimental results in oral and written form. An introduction to reading and understanding of primary scientific literature is presented. Experiments include photosynthesis, water relations, growth regulator effects and host-pathogen interactions.  </description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>BIOL304</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>BIOL303L(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL305" name="Comparative Animal Physiology" credits="3">
	<description>Functional features of whole organisms and their component organs and organ systems will be studied. Emphasis will be on ways in which diverse organisms at various phylogenetic levels perform similar functions. Examples of topics include osmoregulation, gas exchange, control systems, sensors, effectors, brain and behavior.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>BIOL303(C)</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>PHYS122*|PHYS122(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="BIOL305L" name="Comparative Animal Physiology Laboratory" satisfies="LAB" credits="2">
	<description>A laboratory designed to study experimentally selected organismic functions discussed in BIOL 305.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>BIOL303L(C)</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>BIOL305*|BIOL305(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CHEM101" name="Principles of Chemistry I" satisfies="S" credits="4">
	<description>An introduction to chemistry for science majors and other students who require a thorough grounding in the principles of chemistry. Topics treated include the atomic-molecular theory of matter, stoichiometry, states of matter, chemical nomenclature, energetics of chemical and physical processes, solutions, periodic properties, VSEPR, molecular orbital theory and chemistry of familiar elements. </description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="CHEM102" name="Principles of Chemistry II" satisfies="S" credits="4">
	<description>Principles of chemical and physical equilibrium, liquids and solids, elementary thermodynamics, electron and proton transfer reactions, electrochemistry, chemical kinetics and a further study of the periodic properties of the elements.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CHEM101(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="CHEM102L" name="Introductory Chemistry Lab I" satisfies="LAB" credits="2">
	<description>Companion course to CHEM 102, intended for all students who require two or more years of chemistry.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CHEM101</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>CHEM102*</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="PHYS121" name="Introductory Physics I" satisfies="S" credits="4">
	<description>This course emphasizes classical mechanics. Topics include force, particle kinematics and dynamics, equilibrium, Newton's laws of motion and gravitation, rotational motion, collisions, momentum, energy and conservation laws.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH151</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="PHYS122" name="Introductory Physics II" satisfies="S" credits="4">
	<description>This course emphasizes electricity, magnetism, heat and thermodynamics. Topics include Coulomb's law, Gauss's law, electric fields and electric potential, currents, simple circuits and Kirchhoff's laws, generation of magnetic fields by charges in motion, electromagnetic induction, magnetic materials, oscillatory circuits, temperature, heat and the laws of thermodynamics.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>MATH152</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>PHYS121</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="PHYS122L" name="Introductory Physics Laboratory" satisfies="LAB" credits="2">
	<description>Three hours of laboratory work a week and one lecture hour. This is the laboratory course associated with the PHYS 121-122 sequence. </description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>PHYS122*|PHYS122(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="PHYS224" name="Introductory Physics III" credits="3">
	<description>This course emphasizes vibrations, wave motion and optics. Topics include mathematical characterization of vibrations and waves, sound, superposition ofstanding waves, geometrical and physical optics, diffraction, interference and polarization of light.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>PHYS122</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="PHYS304" name="Fundamentals of Astronomy and Astrophysics" credits="3">
	<description>This course presents a calculus-based introduction to key concepts in the science of astronomy and astrophysics. The course is designed for physics majors and other science majors with strong interest in astronomy, physics and mathematics. The course details some of the primary physical concepts relevant to astronomy and astrophysics and also lays the foundation for more advanced coursework in astrophysics.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="GES110" name="Physical Geography" satisfies="S" credits="3">
	<description>Study of the principles and processes of climate, earth materials, landforms, soils and vegetation that give logic to their integrated patterns of world distribution.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="GES111" name="Principles of Geology" credits="3">
	<description>An introduction to the structure, composition, historical evolution and surface features of the earth. Topics include the geologic time scale and radiometric dating; major groups of rocks and minerals; sedimentation and stratigraphy; plate tectonics, seismicity, volcanism, mountain-building and geologic structures; weathering and soil formation; and sculpture of the land by surficial processes.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="GES120" name="Environmental Science and Conservation" credits="3">
	<description>An introduction to the interdisciplinary study of how the earth and the earth's ecosystems work, how they are interconnected, and how humans utilize and impact natural resource systems. Environmental problems and solutions are examined and natural resource conservation strategies and policies are reviewed. Topics covered in the course include ecosystem processes, climate and climate change, biodiversity and endangered species, land degradation and deforestation, human population growth, agriculture, and water and soil resources.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="IS101" name="Introduction to Computer Based Systems" credits="3">
	<description>An overview of computer information systems. This survey course introduces computer hardware, software, procedures, systems and human resources, and it explores their integration and application in business and other segments of society. The fundamentals of computer problem-solving and programming in a higher-level programming language are discussed and demonstrated.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="IS147" name="Introduction to Computer Programming" credits="3">
	<description>This course introduces the basic principles and techniques involved in computer programming and computing. Methods of algorithm development, program development, and program design are taught using an object-oriented programming language. Projects are geared toward those typically encountered in the Information Systems field. </description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="IS246" name="Topics in Programming Languages and Tools" credits="3">
	<description>This course will introduce a high-level programming language or a development tool. The specific language or tool may vary and more than one may be offered (the letter suffix will be used to distinguish them).</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS147|IS246|IS403|IS413|IS448</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS247" name="Computer Programming II" credits="3">
	<description>This second course in a sequence continues the development of programming and problem-solving skills, focusing on topics such as: lists, searching and sorting, sets, stacks, queues, trees and an introduction to analyses of algorithm time and space requirements.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS147(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS300" name="Management Information Systems" credits="3">
	<description>An overview of management information systems (MIS), including the development of transaction processing systems and their relationship to management reporting systems. The course objectives include developing an understanding of the purpose, functions, components and applications of transaction processing systems and management reporting systems in private and public organizations, and describing and evaluating policies for information resource management. </description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="IS303" name="Fundamentals of Human-Computer Interaction" satisfies="AH" credits="3">
	<description>This course provides a survey of human factors and human computer interaction relevant to the design and use of information systems. It describes the contributions of information systems, computer science, psychology, sociology and engineering to human-computer interaction. Emphasis is placed on human factors theories, human information processing concepts, interaction design approaches and usability evaluation methods. Application areas and current research are also reviewed.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS202(C)|IS300(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS304" name="Ethical Issues in Information Systems" credits="3">
	<description>A survey course that reviews the ethical impact of information systems and related technology throughout the world. The course examines the policy issues that relate to the use of information systems, such as persona, privacy, rights of access, security, transborder data flow and confidentiality.</description>
		<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="IS310" name="Software and Hardware Concepts" credits="3">
	<description>A survey of technical topics related to computer systems with emphasis on the relationships between hardware architecture, system software and applications software. The architecture of processors and storage systems are explored, and the implications for systems software design are covered, along with the impact of hardware and system software design on the development of application programs in a business environment.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS125|IS147|CMSC104|CMSC201(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS317" name="Accounting Information Systems" credits="3">
	<description>This course examines accounting systems concepts and technologies, transaction processing systems and the control of accounting information. The roles and uses of technology will be explored in regard to accounting systems design, financial and processing controls, performance evaluation and information security.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>ECON122(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS320" name="Advanced Business Applications" credits="3">
	<description>Students will analyze, design and implement solutions to examples of real-world business problems using advanced database and spreadsheet software that is commonly found in business today. </description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="IS325" name="Introduction to Management Science" credits="3">
	<description>A survey of the concepts and techniques of management science, including decision-making tools, mathematical programming, networks and operations management, and simulation.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS300</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MATH151(C)|MATH155(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS350" name="Business Communications Systems" credits="3">
	<description>A survey of business data communications for end users of computer networks. Students will gain a basic understanding of the features, operations and limitations of different types of communications and network systems. Topics covered include: fundamentals of data and signals, telecommunications systems, wired and wireless media, error control, local-area networks, wide-area networks, the Internet and network security. This course will provide the student the knowledge and ability to interact with the system professional administering these areas.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS300(C)</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MATH155</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS352" name="Women, Gender, and Information Technology" satisfies="SS" credits="3">
	<description>This course examines important issues concerning women, gender and information technology (IT). Students will consider such topics as the history of women's involvement with IT; how women are impacted by technology; how women and girls fare in the educational setting as well as online; and the way gender intersects with IT in relation to other dimensions of women's experience, such as race, class and age. Students will connect issues relevant to women and IT to their own career choices, interact with women in the IT field and utilize technology for research and presentation.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite></prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS361" name="Technology for Management of Aging Services" credits="3">
	<description>This course will introduce students to the history of technology, both as a social/cultural phenomenon that has shaped the lives of those entering their later years as well as an enabler to improve and enhance quality of life for aging Americans.  Students will be introduced to various types of technology and to how they can be used to improve the care and quality of life for aging Americans.  Recent advances in technology such as electronic health records, home monitoring devices, software and tools that enhance seniors' connections with the outside world and turn therapy into recreation, and electronic tools that can be used to manage and enhance an organization's approach to improving its culture and care practices will be examined.  Guest speakers and opportunities to see some of these technologies either in use or through live demonstrations or video will be featured. This is a cross listing of AGING 361. </description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="IS369" name="Research Seminar: Writings in Information Systems" credits="3">
	<description>This seminar course introduces students to current research writing in the fields related to Information Systems. Students will be required to read examples of current research publications in order to improve their professional analytical, communications and interacting skills. The course is designed to improve students skills through reading and critiquing the IS literature, preparing written reviews of journal articles, making presentations, and interacting collaboratively. The content areas for this work will relate to the broad topical areas that encompass the field of information systems that have been encountered through other courses in the program.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>ENGL100</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>IS247(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS370" name="Application Software Development and Documentation using HANDY" credits="3">
	<description></description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="IS387" name="Information Architecture for the Web" credits="3">
	<description>This course focuses on the creation and organization of web content that meets the information needs of end-users and serves the communication purposes of the site's sponsors or creators. Students will learn how to analyze information architecture, navigation, audience and usability of good and bad Websites; conduct online research about best practices; talk with Web content developers from a variety of fields; and develop the Web content plan for a site. </description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="IS403" name="User Interface Design" credits="3">
	<description>A second-semester human computer interaction course in which the student will have the opportunity to apply the user interface theories, guidelines and principles presented in the introductory course. The goal of the course is for the students to follow the complete systems development life cycle in analyzing, designing, developing, implementing and evaluating an interactive user interface. Course activities include producing project milestone deliverables, developing a design report, coding an interactive interface and conducting a formal interface evaluation.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS303(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS404" name="The History of Computers and Computing" credits="3">
	<description></description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="IS410" name="Introduction to Database Design" credits="3">
	<description>This course introduces the student to the process of database development, including data modeling, database design and database implementation. Students learn basic interactive SQL for both data definition and queries. Students practice design skills by developing a small database project.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite></prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS413" name="GUI Systems Using JAVA" credits="3">
	<description></description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS300(B)</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>IS310(B)</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MATH155(C)</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>IS147(C)|CMSC201(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS417" name="Information Systems for Auditors" credits="3">
	<description>nformation Systems Auditing involves the examination of controls within an organization's IT infrastructure. Formerly known as an EDP Audit, the IS Audit involves collecting and evaluating evidence about an organization's systems, practices and operations. This course covers methods and outcomes of those procedures as well as the impact and implications involving controls mandated by governmental agencies.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>ECAC321(C)</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>IS300(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS420" name="Database Application Development" credits="3">
	<description>The course offers hands-on experience for developing client/server database applications using a major database management system. Students learn how to create and manipulate database objects, including tables, views and sequences; develop program units using SQL; and implement client applications such as forms and reports. The course provides students with firsthand experience developing prototype client/server applications.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS410(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS421" name="Database Administration" credits="3">
	<description></description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="IS425" name="Decision Support Systems" credits="3">
	<description>This course provides an overview of theoretical and organizational aspects of decision support systems (DSS), including descriptive and prescriptive decision-making concepts, individual and group decision support systems, and executive information systems. Management of DSS within the end-user environment also is discussed. Projects using DSS software are required, and case examples are discussed.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS410</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MGMT210</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>MATH215</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS427" name="Artificial Intelligence" credits="3">
	<description>This course will provide an introduction to, and hands-on experience with, several artificial intelligence (AI) techniques. It will begin with the concepts and design of knowledge-based systems; the students will identify the issues arising in the design of rule-based systems. Machine learning, particularly neural network topologies will be introduced. The class also will include a discussion of recent advances in AI, including intelligent agents, natural language processing, evolutionary computing and case-based reasoning.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS425(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS428" name="Data Mining Techniques and Applications" credits="3">
	<description>Data mining is the exploration and analysis of large quantities of data in discover hidden and meaningful patterns. Students will learn both how data mining techniques work and how to apply data mining to various business and organizational contexts in this course. Students will gain an in-depth understanding of how data mining is changing the way businesses understand their customers and make decisions.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS410(C)</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>STAT351(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS430" name="Information Systems and Security" credits="3">
	<description>A survey course relating to the establishment and maintenance of a practical information security program. The security implications of databases, telecommunications systems and software are examined, as are techniques to assess risks and to discover abuses of systems.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS300(C)</prerequisite>
		<prerequisite>IS310(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS432" name="Computer Viruses" credits="3">
	<description>Through a review of the current literature, a survey of state-of-the-art software tools and an examination of actual microcomputer-based viruses, the course is intended to prepare students for the eventuality of having to protect their machines and data against the increasingly common threat of viruses.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="IS434" name="The Evolution of Modern Information Systems" credits="3">
	<description>Through a review of the current literature, a survey of state-of-the-art software tools and an examination of actual microcomputer-based viruses, the course is intended to prepare students for the eventuality of having to protect their machines and data against the increasingly common threat of viruses.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="IS436" name="Structured Systems Analysis and Design" credits="3">
	<description>A capstone course involving advanced study and application of structured analysis and design methods throughout the system life cycle. Emphasis is given to the common approaches for gathering requirements, modeling, analyzing and designing information systems. Managing the complexity of system development projects also is addressed. These skills are applied via a semester-long, team-based, field research project.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS410(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS437" name="Applied Systems Design" credits="3">
	<description>Applied Systems Design extends material from IS 436 and allows students to apply material from IS 436 in project teams to create a working Information System. Emphasis is on real-world requirements and constraints. Students may have to sign non-disclosure forms if involved in projects sponsored by organizations providing design opportunities.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="IS438" name="Project Management" credits="3">
	<description>A course covering the manner in which a system project is planned, scheduled and controlled during a project's life. The use of project management techniques such as PERT (Project Evaluation and Review Technique) and Gantt charts will be examined in depth, as will be other techniques of planning, scheduling and controlling projects. </description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="IS439" name="Advanced Project Mangement" satisfied="WI" credits="3">
	<description>Advanced Project Management is a seminar style course that focuses on extending students' project management skills by actively engaging in existing and proposed projects through a case studies approach. Students will take a critical approach to creating and evaluating modern Information Systems projects with the goal of bringing current practice in line with recent research in the field.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS438(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS440" name="Integrating Technology into Business Processes" credits="3">
	<description>Office information and decision support systems are examined as emerging and critical elements in business data and information systems. Emphasis is given to information processing considerations at the systems level, including analysis and management of support activities such as data and records management, electronic filing and retrieving systems, word processing, micro- and repro-graphics, and (tele)communications. The course includes discussion of person/machine interfaces and appraisals of current and future technological trends and their impacts on data processing and office equipment.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS350(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS448" name="Markup and Scripting Languages" credits="3">
	<description>IS 448 covers the history, theory, and practice of markup languages and their associated scripting languages.  This course covers client-side web technology including XHTML, CSS and JavaScript, server-side web technology, such as CGI and PHP, common databases used with web technology, and XML.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>CMSC201(C)|IS147(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS450" name="Data Communications and Networks" credits="3">
	<description>This is an introductory survey course in data communications and networking. It surveys basic theory and technology of computer networking. A single networking protocol stack also is covered in depth. </description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="IS451" name="Network Design and Management" credits="3">
	<description>This course covers implementation and administration of enterprise networking and distributed applications. It includes readings and case studies on middleware, network architecture for distributed applications and selected technologies to support enterprise systems.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS450(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS451M" name="LAN Management Using Microsoft" credits="3">
	<description>A hands-on course using the latest version of the Microsoft server, which covers the design, building, management, security and technical issues involved in a local area network.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS451(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS451U" name="LAN Management Using Unix" credits="3">
	<description>A hands-on course taught in a computer classroom in UNIX operating system management and networking. The design, building, management, security and technical issues involved in a local area network will be covered.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS451(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS452" name="Internetworking" credits="3">
	<description>This course covers network routing and other topics in internetworking. This will be a project-oriented course that will consist of lectures and hands-on laboratory experience creating projects that simulate real-world networks.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS450(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS454" name="Survey of Telecommunications" credits="3">
	<description>This course examines the design and management issues in communications beyond the local area, including wide-area networks, high speed data transfer, integrated voice and data communications, distributed processing and internetworking.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS450(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS456" name="Telecommunications Policy" credits="3">
	<description>This course presents and discusses current telecommunications policy issues based on technological advances and both national and international regulatory developments. The course provides a background in the development and progression of telecommunications regulation and discusses the impact of such policies on various segments of the telecommunications industry.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS450(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS460" name="Health Care Informatics I" credits="3">
	<description>The focus of this course is on health care information systems. Examples of topics covered include: requirements and design, providers and payers, regulations, e-commerce, privacy and security, personnel and vendors, knowledge and diffusion.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS300(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS461" name="Health Care Informatics II" credits="3">
	<description>The focus of this course is on advanced topics in health care information systems. Examples of topics include e-commerce standards, government regulation of privacy and security, and cancer information systems.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS460(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS464" name="Telemedicine in Trauma Care" credits="3">
	<description>This course addresses topical issues of telemedicine in prehospital and trauma care. It covers issues in designing, developing, deploying and evaluating telemedicine systems; research methodologies, including field and laboratory experimentation; and the role of information technologies in supporting team coordination in trauma care from the accident scene to the emergency room. Students will be exposed to the ongoing telemedicine research projects and state-of-the-art telemedicine systems at the Shock Trauma Center.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS461(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS474" name="Legal Aspects of Information Systems" credits="3">
	<description>This course focuses on the legal issues surrounding the use and misuse of computer-stored information and copyrights and piracy of computer software.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>IS300(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="IS498" name="Special Topics in Information Systems" credits="3">
	<description>Topics in the design and implementation of information processing systems.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="MGMT210" name="The Practice of Management" credits="3">
	<description>The study of the role of the manager in leading and controlling organizations ranging from small entrepreneurships to large corporate environments. Topics will include management theories, corporate culture, goal-setting and measuring performance.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="ECON101" name="Principles of Microeconomics" satisfies="SS" credits="3">
	<description>Basic economic principles and their policy applications: value and price for the firm and industry in different competitive situations, public policy toward the firm, income distribution, elements of international economics and comparative economic systems.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="ECON102" name="Basic economic principles and their policy applications: economic methods and institutions, measurement of aggregate economic activity, national income determination, business cycles and economic growth, and elements of aggregate economic policies such as monetary and fiscal policy."  credits="3" satisfies="SS">
	<description>Basic economic principles and their policy applications: economic methods and institutions, measurement of aggregate economic activity, national income determination, business cycles and economic growth, and elements of aggregate economic policies such as monetary and fiscal policy.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="ECON121" name="Principles of Accounting I" credits="3">
	<description>The principles of financial accounting for individuals and business entities, including the use of accounting data in making business decisions and public policy.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="ECON122" name="Principles of Accounting II" credits="3">
	<description>Continuation of ECON 121.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>ECON121(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="ENGL100" name="Composition" credits="3">
	<description>A workshop in writing. The approaches to this course may vary in individual sections, but the aim is to help students write clearly and effectively.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="ENGL393" name="Technical Writing" credits="3">
	<description>This course is designed to teach students with diverse backgrounds and interests how to communicate technical information effectively. With the course's emphases on critical thinking, synthesis and analysis, students learn how to inform and persuade in technical writing style and document design. These documents are applicable to a number of disciplines and to the workplace, and they demonstrate how text and visuals work together to reach various audiences with specific needs. Students also work to develop oral communication, technological andvisual literacy, and collaborative skills.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>ENGL100(C)</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="PHED" name="Physical Education Course" credits="0">
	<description>Any 1.5 credit course which satifies a physical rducation requirement.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="AH1" name="Arts/Humanities Course Discipline 1" credits="3">
	<description>Any course with AH designation: first discipline.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="AH2" name="Arts/Humanities Course Discipline 2" credits="3">
	<description>Any course with AH designation: second discipline.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="SS1" name="Social Sciences Course Discipline 1" credits="3">
	<description>Any course with a SS designation: first discipline</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="SS2" name="Social Sciences Course Discipline 2" credits="3">
	<description>Any course with a SS designation: second discipline</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="M" name="Mathematics Course" credits="3">
	<description>Any course with an M designation</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="S" name="Science Course" credits="3">
	<description>Any course with an S designation</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="LAB" name="Science Course Lab Designation" credits="2">
	<description>Any course with lab designation, denoted by the letter L following the course number.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="C" name="Culture Course" credits="3">
	<description>Any course with the C designation</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="LANG101" name="Language Course 101" credits="3">
	<description>Any 101 level language course.</description>
	<prerequisites/>
</course>
<course id="LANG102" name="Language Course 102" credits="3">
	<description>Any language course at the 102 level.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>LANG101</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
<course id="LANG201" name="Language Course 201" credits="3">
	<description>Any language course at the 201 level.</description>
	<prerequisites>
		<prerequisite>LANG102</prerequisite>
	</prerequisites>
</course>
</courses>